Finding Aid for Finns in America: Printed Materials Related to the Finnish in America and Their Temperance, Religious, Educational, Labor, and Other Activities.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Finns in America: Printed Materials Related to the Finnish in America and Their Temperance, Religious, Educational, Labor, and Other Activities. circa 1914-1977
Finns in America
2009131 Aa 2
Finns in America is an artificial collection assembled to bring together a variety of miscellaneous printed material related to the Finnish experience in the United States.
2 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The Finns in America collection was assembled from items donated individually or as part of other collections.
The collection is open to research.
Finns in America is an artificial collection assembled to bring together a variety of miscellaneous printed material related to the Finnish experience in the United States.
The collection is arranged by subject categories and thereunder by author/title.
Finns in America includes a variety of literary and historical works including songbooks, almanacs, novels, political tracts, emigration manuals, dictionaries, exhibit catalogs and religious publications.
Subjects:
Finnish Americans.
- Education
  - Arminen, K.V. English and Finnish Dictionary (Third, revised edition. Hancock, Mich. 1914.) (Box 1)
  - Kansanvalistus-Seuran Kalenteri [The Calendar of the People's Education Society] 1905 (I. Brooklyn, NY 1905.) (Box 1)
    (almanac, statistics, articles)
  - Lukukirja Amerikan suomalaisille lapsille I [-II]. Toimittaneet Alma Haapanen, Lydia Kangas, K.H. Mannerkorpi, Miina Perttula, B.V. Rautanen. [Textbook for Finnish-American Children. Edited by Alma Haapanen, Lydia Kangas, K.H. Mannerkorpi, Miina Perttula, B.V. Rautanen] (Hancock, Mich. 1905-1916.) (Box 1)
  - Suomi College Bulletin"Pääsiäis-,Juhannus-, Uskonpuhdistuksen muisto-ja Joululehti." 27 (numbers: 1-4/1955 1-3/1956 2-4/1957 1-4/1958 1-4/1959 1-4/1960 1-4/1961 2/1962. Hancock, Mich.) (Box 1)
    (four numbers a year)
  - Suomi-Opiston Viesti [The Message of Suomi College]. (No. 2/1972. Hancock, Mich. 1972) (Box 1)
    (a bulletin, 3-4 times a year)
  - Suomian 1949. (Suomi College, Hancock, Michigan. Hancock, Mich. 1949.) (Box 1)
    (Suomi College in 1949 staff, students, activities)
  - Syyslehti. Suomi-Raamattukoulu. [The Autumn Paper. Suomi-Bible School 1928] (Hancock, Mich. 1928) (Box 1)
    (the Bible school of Suomi College 1927-28; essays)
- Emigration
  - Bogdanoff, Orvo, and Ismo Söderling. "I Feel such a Longing...": Finnish-American Postcards Exhibition Catalog. (Turku, Finland: Institute of Migration, 1988.) (Box 1)
  - Delaware 350: The Beginning of Finnish Migration to the New World: Exhibition Catalogue. (Turku, Finland: Institute of Migration, 1988.) (Box 1)
  - Ilmonen, S. John Morton. Signer of the Declaration of Independence of the United States of America. (Translated by John Wargelin. Hancock, Mich. 1937.) (Box 1)
  - Korkiasaari, Jouni. Suomalaiset Maailmalla. (Turku: Siirtolaisuusinstituutti-Migrationsinstitutet, 1989.) (Box 1)
  - Manual of the United States. For the Information of Immigrants. (Washington, D.C. 1921) (Box 1)
  - Söderling, Ismo. Maassamuuton Ulottuvuudet. (Turku: Turun Yliopisto, 1988.) (Box 1)
  - van Cleef, Eugene Finland-the Republic Farthest North. The Response of Finnish Life to its Geographic Environment. (Box 1)
    (one chapter on Finnish immigration)
  - Virtanen, Keijo. The migration of Finnish-Americans to Florida after World War II. From: Turun Historiallinen Arkisto 31, 1976. (Box 1)
  - Virtanen, Keijo. Pohjois-Amerikassa olevien suomalaisten siirtolaisten ja kotimaan yhteydet 1900-luvulla. From: Eripainos Tornionlaakson Vuosikirjasta, 1981. (5574) (Box 1)
- Labor
  - Alanne, V.S. Kuluttajaosuustoiminnan perusteet. [The Basic Features of the Co-operative Movement] Superior, Wis. 1937. (Box 1)
  - Kolehmainen, John I. Sow the Golden Seed: A History of the Fitchburg (Massachussetts) Finnish-American Newspaper Raivaaja (The Pioneer) 1905-1955. (Fitchburg, Mass. 1955.) (Box 1)
  - Köyhälistön nuija. [The Hammer of the Proletariat] (No. VI/1912. Hancock, Mich. 1912.) (Box 1)
    (a Marxist annual: articles, poetry)
  - Lahtinen, William, ed. 50 vuoden varrelta. [The Past 50 Years]. (Superior, Wis., 1953). (Box 1)
    (the history of Työmies (Workingman) newspaper, a Communist Finnish newspaper in America)
- Literature
  - Aho, G.A. Umpuja. [Buds]. (Ironwood, Mich., 1920.) (Box 1)
  - Andrejew, Leonid Valhe. ([A Lie] Kaleva, Mich. 1907.) (Box 1)
    (a short story, translation)
  - Cobb, Sylvanus, Jr. Itämaan helmi. Kertomus. [The Pearl of the East] (Second Printing. Kaleva, Mich. 1907). (Box 1)
    (translation, novel)
  - Doyle, Conan. Verenimijän uhri. Toinen-osa. [The Victim of the Vampire. Second Part.] (Kaleva, Mich. 1907.) (Box 1)
    (a novel, translation)
  - Freytag, Gustav Ingraban. Historiallinen romaani. ([Ingrabam. Historical Novel] Hancock, Mich. 1909.) (Box 1)
    (translation)
  - Haggard, H. Rider Aarteen etsijät eli Sumun kansa. [Treasure Hunters or People of the Fog]. (New York Mills, Minn. 1902.) (Box 1)
  - Hillilä, Hugo, [t.p. missing. Possibly Tuokiokuvia] n.p. 1917. (Box 1)
    (poetry)
  - Hillalä, Hugo Tuokiokuvia II. [Moments II] (Hancock, Mich. 1944.) (Box 1)
  - Hillilä, Hugo Valinkauhassa. [The Choice]. (Hancock, Mich. 1950.) (Box 1)
    (religious poetry)
  - Johansson, Matti Manifestin maininkeja. [Waves of the Manifesto] (Hancock, Mich. 1904.) (Box 1)
    (poetry dealing with the Manifesto the Russians gave to Finland in 1899. The purpose of the Manifesto was to bind the Finns tighter to the Russian empire than before.)
  - Jokai, Mauri Hiuskihara. Historiallinen romaani. [Hair. Historical Novel] (Brooklyn, N.Y. 1899). (Box 1)
  - "Koivun Visa," Rauniola Suomesta ja Amerikasta. [Rauniola from Finland and America]. (Hancock, Mich. 1915.) (Box 1)
    (novel)
  - "Koivun Visa," Rauniolta. (Hancock, Mich. 1918.) (Box 1)
  - Kolehmainen, John I. Epic of the north: the story of Finland's Kalevala. (New York Mills, Minn., 1973. (6640)) (Box 1)
  - Luoto, Lauri Kamaran sankarit. Valkosen leijonan metsästäjät. II:nen osa. [The Heroes of Kamara. Hunters of the White Lion. Part II.] (Superior, Wis. 1927.) (Box 1)
    (a novel describing the Finnish Civil War in 1918)
  - Nuori Suomi. (Amerikan suomalaisten joulualbumi IV. Duluth, Minn. 1906. Also, no. V, 1907.) (Box 1)
    (Bound together)
  - Parkkila, John. Siirtolaisen kannel. [The Immigrant's Harp]. (Hancock, Mich. 1907.) (Box 1)
  - Ruokasmake, John Tunnetko Jumalaa luomisen töiss ä? [Do You Know Your God?] (Hancock, Mich. 1932.) (Box 1)
    (religious novel)
  - Salonen, Alex. Rulkurin Rujilla. Rokoelma runoja. (Hancock, Mich., 1902.) (Box 1)
    (poetry (5722))
  - Stevenson, R.L. Aarresaari. [Treasure Island] (Kaleva, Mich., 1904.) (Box 1)
  - A Finnish-American novel (No place, no date.) (Box 1)
    (no title page)
- Miscellaneous
  - Almanakka vuodeksi 1953. [Almanac for 1953]. (Hancock, Mich. 1952.) (Box 2)
  - Helsinki University Library. List of Finnish and foreign newspapers on microfilm. (1965.) (Box 2)
  - Joulu [Christmas] 1958. (Duluth, Minn. 1958.) (Box 2)
    (Finnish-American independent Finnish language magazine)
  - Kalevainen [The Kaleva People]. (Hancock, Mich.; Brooklyn, N.Y.) (Box 2)
    (a magazine for the Ladies and Knights of Kaleva)
    - 1939, 1941, 1943, 1944, 1947, 1954, 1956, 1957, 1958, 1960, 1961, 11 volumes
- Music
  - Matkalla. Taskulaulukirja. [Traveling. A Pocket Song Book] (Hancock, Mich. 1918.) (Box 2)
    (religious songs)
  - Raittiuslaulukirja. Raittiusjuhlia, huwimatkoja ja raittiuskokoukjia warten. (Hancock, Mich., 1899.) (Box 2)
  - Siionin lauluja. Toimittanut Suomi-Synodi. [Songs of Zion. Edited by Suomi Synod] (Second, revised edition. Hancock, Mich. 1924.) (Box 2)
- Politics
  - Immonen, Kari. Talous, Kulttuuri ja kansainväliset suhteet. (University of Turku, 1979) (Box 2)
  - "Munkki Iliodor," Venäjän keisarillisen perheen salaisuuksia. [The Secrets of the Russian Tsarist Family] (Duluth, Minn. 1917.) (Box 2)
  - Pulli, E.A. Sota Pohjan perillä. Miksi Suomessa käytiin sotaa ja mitä sen aikana tapahtui. [The War in the North. Why There was a War and What Happened While It Lasted] (Duluth, Minn. 1940.) (Box 2)
    (story of the Winter War 1939-40)
  - Sulkanen, Elis, Pysvvä rauha tai ihmiskunnan tuho. Yhteis-kunnallinen tutkimus rauhan perusteista; suurvaltapolitiikka ja pienet maat. Katsaus Suomen asemaan maailmansodan aikana. [Lasting Peace or Disaster to Humanity. A Study of the Bases of Peace; World Power Politics and Small Countries. A Survey to Finland's Situation during the World War]. (Fitchburg, Mass. 1946.) (Box 2)
- Religion
  - Amerikan Suometar [The Finn in America] December 5, 1961. (Hancock, Mich.) (Box 2)
    (Finnish-American religious newspaper)
  - Build and Grow ([Suomi Zion Lutheran Church. Fairport Harbor, Ohio. n.p., undated]) (Box 2)
    (a publication to get money for the new building)
  - Heräävä nuoriso. [Young People Awakening] (No. 12/1936. Lapua, Finland.) (Box 2)
    (religious periodical)
  - Isien kirkko. Suomi-Synodin Ohio-Pa. piirin kevätjulkaisu 1929. [The Church of Fathers. The Spring Publication of Suomi Synod, Ohio-Pennsylvania District 1929] (Hancock, Mich. 1929.) (Box 2)
    (religious essays)
  - Kukkonen, Walter J. Onko koko maailma autuas? (Hancock, Mich., 1953.) (Box 2)
  - Kylvömailta. Suomi-Synodin entisten ja nykyisten pappien saarnoja. Toisen vuosikerran evankeliumiteksteista. [From Sowing Fields. Sermons of the Pastors of Suomi Synod] (Hancock, Mich. 1928.) (Box 2)
  - Luterilainen. Luterilainen perhelehti. Joulunumero 1957, 1959. [The Lutheran. A Lutheran Family Magazine. Christmas Number 1957 1959.] (Lahti, Finland 1957, 1959.) (Box 2)
  - The Lutheran Counselor. (Hancock, Mich.) (Box 2)
    Issues for July 1, 1958, July 16, 1958, August 1, 1958, June 16, 1960 (Suomi Synod 70th Anniversary Issue); June 1, 1962.
  - Messiah Lutheran Church (Duluth, Minn.). Church Directory. (Duluth, Minn. 1972.) (Box 2)
  - Nuorison kevät 1920. I.A.S.E.L.K.N.Y:n liiton kevätjulkaisu. [The Spring of Youth. The Spring Publication of the League of Finnish Evangelical Lutheran Young People's Association of Eastern America] (Hancock, Mich. 1920.) (Box 2)
    (essays, poetry)
  - Nuorison ystäv ä. [Young People's Friend] (No. 4/1954. Helsinki 1954.) (Box 2)
    (religious periodical; essays)
  - Nuorten Ystävä. Omistettu Idän piirin Kr. Nuorisoyhdis-tyksille. [The Friend of Young People. Dedicated to the Christian Youth Associations of the East] No. 5, May 1921. (Hancock, Mich. 1921.) (Box 2)
    (articles)
  - Paananen, Emil J. Armoitettuja [The Blessed]. (Hancock, Mich., [1947 ?].) (Box 2)
  - Pajala, Toivo Eräs ajan merkki. [A Sign of Today] (Vancouver B.C. 1965.) (Box 2)
    (religious essay)
  - Raamatun Historia. Amerikan suomalaista nuorisoa varten. Toimittanut J.K. Nikander. [The History of the Bible. For the Finnish-American Youth. Edited by J.K. Nikander] (Hancock, Mich. 1915.) (Box 2)
  - Raamatun tutkisteluja. Ensimäinen osa. Jumalallinen aikakausien suunnitelma. [The Studies of the Bible. First part. A Plan for the Periods of God]. (Brooklyn, N.Y. no date.) (Box 2)
  - Rutherford, J.F. Jumalan harppu. Todistaa sitovasti, että miljoonat nykyisin elävistä eivät koskaan kuole. Tekstikirja Raamatun tutkimista varten erikoisesti sovellettu aloittelijoille; lukuisine kysymyksineen ja vastauksineen. [The Harp of God. Proves that Millions of People Never Die. A Text Book for Studying Bible, Especially for Beginners; with Many Questions and Reference to the Bible] (Helsinki 1922.) (Box 2)
  - Sanansaattaja. [The Apostle] (No. 12/1961. Helsinki 1961.) (Box 2)
  - Suomalainen. Yhdysvaltain ja Canadan Suomi-konferenssin kuukausijulkaisu. [The Finn. Monthly Bulletin of Suomi Conference in USA and Canada] (Hancock, Mich.)
    - December 1962, February 1963, April 1963, May 1963, July 1963, January, 1964, April 1964, May 1964, December 1964, 9 volumes (Box 2)
  - Suomalainen Virsikirja evankelis-lutherilaisille seurakunnille. [Finnish Hymn Book for Evangelic-Lutheran Congregations] (Turku, Finland 1889.) (Box 2)
  - Suomalainen Virsikirja evankelis-luteerilaisille seruakunnille Suomessa ja Amerikan Yhdysvalloissa. [Finnish Hymn Book for Evangelic-Lutheran Congregations in Finland and in the United States] (Hancock, Mich. 1918.) (Box 2)
  - Suomen Evankelis-Lutherisen kirkon katekismus. [The Official Textbook of the Finnish Evangelic-Lutheran Church] (Hancock, Mich. 1915 1929.) (Box 2)
  - Suomi Kirkko 1891-1941. Fairport Harbor, Ohio. Riemuvuoden julkaisu. [Suomi Church 1891-1941 Fairport Harbor, Ohio. Publication for the Jubilation Year]. (Hancock, Mich. 1941.) (Box 2)
  - Suomi-Konferenssin 5. vuosijuhlat kesäkuun 16, 17, 18, 1967. St. Ansgarin luterilainen kirkko, Lawrence Avenue, and Avenue Road, Toronto, Ontario, Canada. [The 5th Anniversary Celebration of Suomi Conference (Lutheran Church in America) on June 16, 17, and 18, 1967. St. Ansgar's Lutheran Church, Lawrence Avenue and Avenue Road, Toronto, Ontario, Canada.] (n.p. 1967 .) (Box 2)
    (program and greetings)
  - Suomi Zion Lutheran Church, Fairport Harbor, Ohio. Annual Report, 1957 1961. (Box 2)
  - Suomi Zion Lutheran Church. Fairport Harbor, Ohio. Luther Center. Dedication. Sunday, September 29, 1957. (n.p. 1957.) (Box 2)
  - Torvinen, John. Jesus Kristus on tie syntisille uskon kautta vanhurskauteen, elämään ja rauhaan. (Hancock, Mich., [n.d.]) (Box 2)
  - Torvinen, John. Terveellinen oppi. (Calumet, Mich. 1938.) (Box 2)
  - Wasunta, Arne. Usko, rukous ja farisealaisuus [Faith, Prayer, and Pharisaism]. (Ironwood, Mich., 1922.) (Box 2)
  - [Unidentified hymnal in Finnish, n.p., n.d.] (Box 2)
- Temperance
  - Kevät-Albumi 1902. [Spring Album 1902] (Hancock, Mich. 1902.) (Box 2)
  - Rauhankokous ja pääpiirteitä Amerikan suomalaisten raittiustyön historiasta. [The Peace Meeting and Main Characteristics of the History of the Finnish-American Temperance Movement] (Hancock, Mich. 1908.) (Box 2)
  - Valoa. Amerikan suomalaisen raittiuskansan kesäjulkaisu 1944. [Light. The Summer Publication of Finnish-American Temperance People] (n.p. 1944.) (Box 2)